hello this is Frankie Freitas and
welcome to another week of whole talk
for the week of February 1st 1999.
we have a very interesting guest this
week John Claire who packs his
philosophy equipment up and takes it
down into caves to make Holograms of the
formations
John just made his first laser pointer
hologram so he's happy he doesn't have
to tie the heavy power pack around his
leg to crawl for over an hour to get
where he's going inside the cave
just pop the pointer in his pocket and
he's good to go
now we have quite a few Updates this
week on the laser pointer front but I'm
going to save the details for next
week's show
reports are coming in from others now
making Holograms using a laser pointer
and it's very encouraging
one person from Norway had his helium
neon laser quit on him over the holidays
and now he's not going to replace it
Steve Michael should have a new report
by next week and I'll be here to tell
you about my own experiment using solar
power to run my laser pointer
Illuminating the needs for Batteries
entirely
you can leave my first report on this on
the laser pointer page
now I just got my 10 milliwatt 640
nanometer laser pointer module actually
a laser diode module in the mail this
week
this past week
so this upcoming week one whole talk
I'll be running some testing to see how
things work out and I'll report on this
as well on next week's show
now my guest John Claire contacted me
last year at the end of the year Justice
Steve and I began to put up information
on making Holograms with laser pointers
he was very interested in this because
he has to Lug his helium Beyond laser
along with a very heavy motorcycle
battery down into the caves with him
ties the motorcycle battery to his leg
as he crawls through the tight crevices
that leads to the larger Cathedral
underground rooms
for John being able to make Holograms
using a laser pointer is a dream come
true
he just needs to pop the pointer in his
pocket and off he goes now he just made
his first successful laser pointer
hologram this week and he's looking to
head into the caves to try it out down
there very soon
I had a lot of fun talking with John and
I think he's doing something that's very
unique with holography and I hope you
enjoy the interview
now I won't be coming back on after the
interview is over so I'll say thank you
for tuning in and hope that you tune in
every week for a new Hollow talk show
this is Frankie Fighters for holotalk
we'll be right back after this quick
message
would you like to make your own
one-of-a-kind hologram and learn how you
can start making holograms on your own
at the same time you can do this and
much more by attending one of Frankie's
greatest holography workshops from
beginner to Advanced Frank's got a
workshop that's just right for you from
single afternoon evening or weekend
introductory workshops to Wednesday
evening five week complete courses and
don't forget your viewers Workshop raise
your coiner holography
located just off the Northeast Extension
of the Pennsylvania Turnpike and
Interstate 78 the studio is a quick
non-stop drive from the New York
Philadelphia and Baltimore Washington DC
areas for more information call the
Studio's toll-free hotline at
1-800-458-3525 and begin your own
Journey with holography today that's
1-800-458-3525 for more information on
attending a Frankie greatest holography
Workshop today
thank you
oh Frank John how are you hi sorry I
went home earlier oh that's that's
perfectly okay
no that's okay I wasn't quite sure if we
were in the same time zone
is it okay 10 o'clock now
it's not too late for you isn't it
but if I remember right with the email
that you sent me the other night you
were like painting a hologram pack at
four in the morning aren't you yeah that
Sunday night or Monday night I remember
doing that well I know those times I'll
tell you what doesn't that paint can
when you shake it with the marble and it
sounded like 10 times as loud in the
middle of the night yeah yeah
the whole neighborhood up because I
usually go outside and spray it and I'm
standing outside shaking this paint can
and you can hear it throughout the whole
neighborhood
so we're talking with John is it player
okay John Claire I just wanted to make
sure that I got the last name for now
because we've been back and forth with
email but we really haven't talked to
one another until just now
and John does something that I think is
so unique
I've never heard about it before now
most of the times when people make
Holograms they're in a laboratory or a
studio environment
but John actually takes his equipment
down into caves right right well you
know I'll try to set up a holography
table you want to get into a basement on
a bedrock at home it would be better
except to get down into the bedroom now
tell me something do you have any
isolation that you take down there or is
that is that cave so still and so
isolated that you just shoot right at
whatever's in there right just the
formation and the
the
holographic plate and set it up again
you know give it a couple seconds to
settle
and then you do your shoot now you were
using the helium neon laser right why
don't you tell us some of the trouble
that you have to go through to get a
helium neon laser because most helium
neon layers and lasers obviously run off
of electricity but I'm sure you don't
have any receptacles down there in the
cave right
what do you have to do to get power down
there
I also how to take I guess it's called a
motorcycle battery which is a kind of a
heavy device down there and then the
laser itself you know Neons what about a
foot and a half long and
it's kind of a rough Journey getting
into the cave so I've put at the bottom
of a piece of I guess four inch PVC pipe
with some padding it all inside of it
okay yeah that's a good idea
uh and then I limited to five milliwatts
because it's the biggest DC power supply
could find the only Power five Miller
one I thought it had a 10 one now we got
the fire now
yeah what do you think about that now
you did a hologram the other night using
your diode right right and it turned out
pretty good for you
turned out beautiful great the first two
I did didn't turn out so well but uh
reports are starting to come in from
people who are doing these diodes and
and even myself my first when I did one
around Christmas time I just grabbed my
wife's Frosty the Snowman and put it
there and it was rather dim and I think
what happens is everyone's so excited
just to see if this works that they just
rushed through everything and don't take
the time like I did I didn't take time I
didn't take a lot of time with it I
wanted to really see if this would work
and it's usually the second or third one
once you see that you at least can get
something
you know that might be possible you know
you slow down a little bit and take a
little bit more time with the pro with
the actual exposure and the processing
and and it really pays off like we had
the hairdryer right away too yeah
okay and the third time I just did let
it sit for a while
but naturally drive before I hit it with
a hair dryer how long have you been
doing this right back in the 70s
sometimes maybe that 73 or 74 first
started now is this first going on and
off uh
professional photographer or anything
just a hobby
now you started making whole grains back
in the 70s is that what you're saying
yeah wow and you were doing it in caves
as well well no I tried doing the cave
way back then but they didn't have these
nice little uh Power Supplies oh okay
yeah I tried dragging a homemade
inverter and all back in there you know
how did you get involved with holography
in the first place are you a technical
person artistic or how would you
describe yourself in your involvement
with holography I don't know when I
first heard about it back in the 60s
when I was in high school and fascinated
and wanted to do it
did you have like a five milliwatt back
there actually oh no yeah
isn't that something no I'm sure there's
probably a proper word for people who go
into caves what's what's the word for
that well proper word to catering
uh some people call it spelunking but uh
we consider sponsors of the amateur
cavers yeah yeah the real cavers cavers
pretty tightens into the spots at
that right
oh yeah yeah this particular one uh
hologram it hit some really beautiful
stuff in Virginia
200 foot long
but that's good because that keeps
people out yeah you have to be pretty
dedicated to go through that much
trouble get back in there yeah if you're
in these uh these small passageways that
you're you're crawling through to
eventually wind up in like one of those
large rooms or something is that is the
formations where there's a quite a large
round
just full of these formations they're
like um made out of look like they're
made out of a cut glass or something
some of them are just transparent
particular formation I did the Hologram
I would look like a little tiny
Christmas tree
believe it's called aragonite the
mineralism made out of she's got a whole
bunch of real shiny little points on it
and it's just perfect though very gently
uh put a four by five inch holographic
plate up against it
aim the laser go and shoot it hello are
you using axle materials right yeah
cut my Supply rounded out yeah
how are you with your supply you still
have quite a few extra materials left
a box and a half left yeah four by five
inch replacement one box of two by twos
some of the old uh film stock too that's
probably the next trick I want to pull
off is doing one of the cone shape
hologram oh yeah
like uh
you just placed the cone right over the
formation I guess right that is on
formation
we only need to use diode shouldn't be
any trouble to put the dye in space so
they're all in the one small block of
wood and
you had to leave it out on some kind of
a pipe or something the real formation
isn't that something how many Holograms
would you say you've done that you have
in your collection
types of holograms over the years and
tried a few different multiplexes
that's the one
Big Trees but it makes 9
Flex Holograms yeah
but it doesn't really turned out really
well but still it's thrilling just to do
it and even get accruity image do you
belong to like a cave group that you
show other people in the group The
Holograms and stuff yeah that's the
National Organization we have a local uh
chapter here called a grotto
that belonged to something called
National epideological custodian and 9
000 people are in that group if
anybody's interested in caves they can
go to the web and the
cave.org that gets you the National
Speed and logical Society okay you want
to know about caves and how to find your
own local Grotto well there's going to
be a lot of them out there probably
listening to this right now do you ever
put things together for an exhibit of
your work
um
put some together that would be so well
received yeah yeah well
there are different National paper
things that go on and on
something coming up in about a month I
was thinking about maybe uh playing one
of these there yeah because everybody
you know in my local group is seeing it
Without Really raved about it yeah is
this one that you made with the pointer
or the uh yeah yeah
probably the shortly going back
underground with the pointer now yeah
now I'm I'm going to put up a web page
where people are actually starting to
make the Holograms now it was first you
know Steve and I were doing it and then
people would log on to the website and
read about what we were doing and now
they're starting doing on on their own
around the world
and I'm going to pull up a web page
where you can see all the different work
that people's been doing making
Holograms using the laser pointer I'd
love to have a photograph of one of your
pieces if it's possible so that I could
put it on the web page do you ever take
photos of them no no I don't know that
much about cameras yeah
so your wife goes with you on these
trips huh oh yeah did she help you out
with the holography
um I wanted to try to make some
holograms for my newsletter for a local
Group which
foreign
small number of them turned out even
halfway decent yeah that's taking that
film and sandwiches between glass now
how do you hold that glass together with
Clips yeah just Clips yeah I didn't use
that guy index matching fluids
well it's one thing is the dusty
environment is Muddy and there's a mess
back in the game that's all you need to
do is mess with some discus liquid too
while you're acting now she's clean
glass and uh
so you get the I guess you call it the
Newton Rings or whatever yeah yeah
look a little bit more artistic yeah
there you go have you ever heard or
worked with triathanolamine yeah
because that actually pre-sensitizes the
emotion you may find out you get a
little bit brighter result you could
probably uh actually soak a couple
plates like five or six plates before
you go down and have them already
pre-treated when you just take them out
of the box and do a shoot you guys shot
sometime that works especially nice with
the laser pointer the ones that I've
shot using triathanol aminer several
times brighter than the ones that have
not been treated and are just exposed
out of the box ultimate exposure time it
still comes up right with Triathlon yeah
you're playing around with changing
colors yeah it is basically but it
actually sensitizes the Emulsion yeah
a hypersensitizing the Emulsion now what
type of laser pointer are you using I
think you sent me an email one time and
said you didn't have much luck with it
right when you first started out because
I was running through a space Builder
and I figured it wouldn't be any good
until I really got a decent pattern
through my space filler and every one of
them I used would never make a really
nice pattern
we had a little bit of leftover
diffraction in them
so it's just a little diffraction in it
I went ahead and tried it anyhow just
amazed now no kidding well
and now you have the laser pointer set
up you have it like is there a button
that you have to press and you put a
clip over that or something yeah well I
just ran a piece of tape around that put
a couple of alligator took the batteries
out laser pointer and stuff a couple
alligator clips into it
hook up to an external battery three uh
e cells oh you use C cells huh
somebody that has a lot of film though
to experiment with because I tried
nothing
experiment a whole lot because I don't
have that much at home
uh
just been bad news the shutter at all I
mean like yeah healing neon you got to
hit a certain amount of time for it to
warm up and I'll get the third week
delivery at the moment yeah is it really
a warm-up time to them so you just turn
it on that's where she's sex turn it off
there you go I did try that one uh the
first two
uh all against traffic the laser diode
we want to use the hand shutter just a
piece of cardboard I did try turning
turning on and
turn it back off but neither one of
those turned out too well but uh what
did you do different than the one that
turned out really nice
and just being a little bit more careful
and all huh
letting it uh naturally dry before I
took the hair dryer to it I guess yeah
that's real important too people don't
realize what happens to that Emulsion
when you uh when you use a hair dryer
that Emulsion collapses
yeah
isn't that something
so if you get a chance could you send me
a couple pictures of your Holograms at
some time
all right that would be great because
I'll tell you what I'm going to do I'm
going to put a show together of of laser
pointer holography and let people have
an opportunity to see what can be done
with laser Corners because this I don't
want to sound off the wall but this is
really a revolution you know I mean I
just I just picked 10 milliwatt laser
pointer not a planter but a diode it
just came up to that yeah it just came
no I I have it set up but I haven't done
any exposure with it yet I'm wondering
if it's really as good as the laser
point it's magic pointers get some kind
of a weird new laser diode in that are
in they get a modules yeah well I'm not
too crazy about the beam the bean is
very rectangular on it and I'm having a
really hard time with it but I'm gonna
have to play around but uh for 10
milliwatts uh I was at a place today
where they wanted 1 280 for a 10
millilitating it's like there's no way
you have to do that anymore
yeah I got a you know me I'm upstairs
extra physics 124 or something like that
that's kind of what it is like 25 35
milliliters then but it died oh yeah
just put that little thing blue
I called a couple of places and the best
price I got so far
several hundred dollars to try to re-gas
the thing or whatever you have to do
yeah but heck now we got these diets
why why even bother
yeah
well John you have anything you want to
add to anything before we uh say good
night here
no that really is it's just uh anybody
in your caving group you'd like to say
hello to in case they log on and listen
to the show
well yeah like uh
thank uh Tom moltz and uh buddy walker
uh for all the help they had to give him
the uh carry the equipment back into the
cave you know
now how many people do you have with you
when you're shooting these Holograms in
the cave well maybe three or four yeah
and how long does it take to get to the
place where you have to shoot it oh you
may want to go into the cave yeah say
you're on the outside of the cave you're
just getting ready to go in how much
time does it take to crawl through that
area before you're in the area where you
shoot the Holograms
oh really yeah
sometimes it's got a little bit of water
in it too wow yeah that's another thing
she was giving back what I'm doing
shooting at uh
there's always a little bit of water
dripping
on
so you have to do some protection to
keep you on the water from dropping
right onto the lens of the space filter
or something like that yeah or getting
onto your plate too while you're sipping
on a plate before you even make an
exposure
nastiest looking water spot huh yeah
yeah I'm looking forward to seeing you
just shoot a hologram for me and send it
to me okay and I'll put it in at the
collection and uh I'm gonna have a
couple coming in from Norway these guys
are just starting to shoot them now I I
got an email from the one guy and he
just wrote to me right in the middle of
the night he was just so happy in this
email that he was able to shoot a
beautiful hologram using a little laser
pointer over there that's something well
I know how excited I went the other
night I mean outside you know running up
and down the driveway jumping around a
little bit and then yeah
well John thanks for being on the show
and it's really unique what you're doing
with holography when I get your hologram
I'm going to take a photo of it here in
the studio and get it up on the website
so that everybody can see some of the
work that you're doing that's very
unique
well John thanks for being on the show
okay if you hold on for just a second
I'll get these headphones off and I'll
pick the phone up okay hold on
foreign